Arnold comes out and says hey next year
the winner of this contest is getting
$500,000 makes it the first bodybuilding
contest to have a cash prize of half a
million dollars the one thing about
Hooper is that he's such a calculated
strong man in ways that like no other
athlete in the sport ever really has
been and everything that Hooper said is
exactly what then happened he just
peered into the future and then that is
the reality that we lived in Wesley
vissers I'm not going to say he came out
of nowhere but he finished in seventh
place last year looking at the Olympia
and going wait a minute okay well we
know what the top four was but now Vis
is in the mix and it's like is Vis
actually going to be standing next to
Bumstead in Final Call
outs hey folks welcome to strength
weekly the weekly internet show that
gives you the full rundown of everything
you need to know around the barbell game
I'm one of your co-hosts David Thomas
town and I'm joined by the much more
intrepid Phillip bman we have a lot to
cover this week a quick reminder go
ahead subscribe to Barb Ben on YouTube
you're watching already give us that
subscription that sweet sweet
subscription it also gives us validation
we got a lot to cover this week because
the Arnold is done the yearly sports
festival fitness expo series of
competitions in colubus Ohio happened
Phil what a weekend it was how are you
feeling after all that coverage yeah I'm
feeling good I'm feeling tired but
excited there were a lot of standout
performances we called a bunch of things
right but we also called a bunch of
things wrong which I'm very excited to
get into because I love it when that
happens so yeah was it was a big contest
for both bodybuilding and strong men and
strong women so a lot to talk about
today well let's get to the Run of show
because it's what the people want first
up we're covering the men's open
bodybuilding division Hadi chupen of
Iran takes the win Mitchell Hooper the
Canadian strongman Force defends his
title and repeats as the Arnold
strongman classic Champion we also talk
about how hawor bordon did and actually
that is one thing that Phil and I
basically predicted almost exactly
correct correctly we're talking about
strong woman Lucy underdown pulling a
new elephant bar deadlift record 666
it's not the mark of the beast it's the
new women's Elephant bar deadlift record
we're going to talk about why that's
important finally Wesley visser's huge
upset in the men's classic physique
competition maybe the biggest upset of
the weekend was it the biggest upset of
the weekend so I would say so I think
that that's that is the mark of it was
clear that those guys were the top two
based on the final call outs but like
even the commentary team was just like
you know Ramon's too good his waist is
too tight like there's just no way don't
give it away Phil we're gonna go into
that we're gonna go into we're going
into sorry we're going into this is
called foreshadowing okay without
further Ado let's get into it Phil we
got to talk about the men's open
bodybuilding division because a lot
happened not only about who won but the
the contest itself the battle itself
between hottie and Samson Samson is such
a good name for a bodybuilder I still
can't get over
that yeah Arnold Schwarzenegger making
an historic maybe gamechanging
announcement maybe it might change
bodybuilding as we know it let's talk
about the two men at the top okay you
got Samson and hottie Phil hotti shupin
give us a quick recap of his last like
three years in bodybuilding for those
who have been living under a rock okay
so we all remember when big Ramy was the
Mr Olympia right big Ramy went back
toback at the Olympia but his second
year hadti shupin came up uh like onto
the top of the scene and everybody in
big ramy's second win thought that that
year was the year hadti should have won
his conditioning was on point he has a
midsection like nobody else in the game
and it was arguable in the same way that
when big Ramy won his first title that
hotti should have won his first title a
year before he actually did so there was
discrepancy there then the following
year hotti gets the win and then this
past year he loses the title derck lford
in a debatable contest where you could
have argued for either guy because they
had strengths uh both Lunsford and
hottie at the top and then in third
place right behind them behind Lunsford
and shupin was Samson daa in third place
at the 2023 Olympia so because hadti
didn't win at the Olympia he's like okay
I actually have to come back and make my
presence known so that I can build some
momentum to try and challenge lford
again to reclaim the title in 2024 so
he's like all right I'm going to compete
at the Arnold Classic so it's the second
and third place finishers at the 2023
Olympia clashing again at the Arnold
Classic in Columbus this past weekend I
just going to say one additional Ripple
is that Samson Duda he took the Arnold
Classic title in 2023 surprised a lot of
people brought insanely good package to
the stage he was not someone the experts
called to take the title in 2023 the
Arnold Classic title right and it really
thrust him onto the scene as a potential
Olympia Contender he goes on to Podium
at the Olympia
so for him he's trying to defend his
Arnold Classic
title hottie coming out hot wants to
regain the Olympia and a good way to
build momentum doing that is to compete
in the Aral classic we often see Olympia
winners in the men's open division not
compete in the Arnold Classic the
following year right a great example
Derrick lford not competing in the
Arnold Classic the year after he won the
Olympia just focusing on repeating as Mr
Olympia
hottie he's he's back he's going to do
two comps this year right he's going to
do the the AR classic and the Olympia so
and hottie he brings an insane package
hottie brings an unbelievably
conditioned package and that's what sets
him apart so the difference though
between daa and chupen at this contest
really came down to just conditioning I
mean they're both extremely muscularly
dense through all of their posing the
real Difference Maker is chupen has the
absolute most insane conditioning of
anybody in the division his seratus pose
like during during anything that's
abdominals it's just like carved all the
way through like down his entire
midsection and I think that that's what
set him apart here because the eye
continuously gets drawn to that
conditioning that chupin brings now on
your comment before about like how the
Olympian Champion doesn't often compete
at other shows outside of the Olympia
that's for that's twofold one is because
it's really hard to get down to
competition shape multiple times
throughout a season like it is very hard
to go through a prep and recover and do
all that like it's tough on the body but
secondly if you miss right like if a
champion comes in and is just like
slightly Off the Mark and loses it it's
like okay well what does that mean for
them you know like this is a subjective
sport you don't want to carry that kind
of stuff so it is a gamble to compete
outside of the Olympia if you are the
Olympia Champion a couple additional
awards that were actually given out
before the podium was before the winter
was announced hottie won the Franco
Columbo most muscular award the most
muscular award often rewards the guy who
shows up with the most muscularity the
greatest amount ount of muscularity
relative to their frame Samson Duda won
the Ed corny best poser award top two
guys swept all the awards they swept one
and two and then they swept most
muscular and best poser really shows the
level competition uh that these guys
brought against each other and and that
they really stood out from the pack so
hottie wins
$300,000 Arnold comes out and says hey
next year the winner of this contest is
getting
$500,000 which makes it the richest
purse in bodybuilding history makes it
the first bodybuilding contest to have a
cash prize of half a million dolls and
guess what unless something changes at
the Olympia it makes it a richer purse
than the Olympia because right now Mr
Olympia gets 400k yeah to cavia it is
500,000 to the men's Open winner uh
there will be increases in the other
divisions as well but the only number
that we've actually confirmed and heard
from Arnold himself is the men's Open
winner gets 500k as opposed to the 300K
that D Duda won last year and that
shupin won this year and yeah 400k at
for the Mr Olympia title which has been
standard for some number of years now
Arnold's not shy about much these days
he's challenging the Olympia and saying
we're putting our money where our mouth
is we're gonna make this the richest
prize in
bodybuilding and maybe what that does is
it increases the incentive for the
reigning Mr Olympia maybe incentivizes
them to compete at the Arnold right so
we don't know exactly what's going to
happen here but it's a really big
statement by Arnold and event organizers
David I have a question for you if if
Arnold is coming at the Olympia saying
that he wants the aror classic to
compete if not be the top show in
bodybuilding the argument from the
Olympia side pretty much has to just be
well you can't be the top contest in
bodybuilding if you're only covering
seven of 11 ifb pro ifbb pro divisions
where where where where's the stance on
that how how does how should the Arnold
Classic navigate that can they remain
can they ever be the top show if they're
not covering all 11 divisions or are the
other athletes if they want to compete
at the show just going to have to figure
out where they slot into the seven that
they do actually cover yeah I think
that's a great question Phil I think
there's something to be said here for
Arnold on stage only announcing the
increase for the men's open division it
seems to me like he's saying we're
focused on making this contest the men's
open contest one of seven bodybuilding
uh divisions that that are contested at
the Arnold making this the premier men's
open and maybe the others follow over
time right but I think it's telling that
classic physique men's classic physique
has quickly become maybe the most
popular division in bodybuilding and the
price purse at the Arnold for classic
physique is relatively small compared to
men's open and Arnold has actually said
that he thinks classic physique is the
future of bodybuilding right he says
that but he didn't come out and say that
during the classic physique and say oh
we're gonna beat we're gonna have this
big prize pull for classic physique he's
only saying it for the men's open and I
think what he's trying to do is trying
to position the Arnold as maybe the
premier bodybuilding competition for
this first for this one division
first so I think he's focused on kind of
conquering that mount his Everest and
then you get the other mountains as well
after that that that's my that's my take
that's a great question it's a good take
yeah I I when he announced it and it's
like okay the argument is is the Arnold
Classic going to become the biggest
contest the immediate argument back is
you can't be the top contest if you
don't cover all of the divisions that
are you know part of ifbb Pro so it's
like that I I I think that there's some
debate there but I think that your your
take makes a lot of sense it's exciting
it's an exciting time but there's it's
open-ended you know well let's move on
we gotta move on to another sport where
the the competitions are kind of duking
it out for who's number one and that is
strongman men's open strongman Mitchell
Hooper repeats as Arnold strongman
classic
Champion he's also the reigning world's
strongest man he's on a bit of it he's
not undefeated he's not undefeated in
competition over the last year that's
certainly just hasn't missed a Podium
Mitchell Hooper put on a really
interesting performance we're going to
talk about Mitchell Hooper then we're
going to talk about everyone else
Mitchell Hooper was we have seen him
kind of fall into this pattern and
you've identified this Phil where he
takes an early lead and then uses his
gamesmanship and planning to maintain
that lead over the course of a weekend
did not happen here he had some serious
ground to make up heading into day two
of competition Phil can you give us the
The Cliffs notes the short version of
Hooper's trajectory back to the top of
the podium and defending his title yeah
serious ground is is variable because
for Hooper it's is less significant than
it would be for any other athlete in the
game right now the one thing about
Hooper is that he's such a calculated
strong man in ways that like no other
athlete in the sport ever really has
been where he's just so open about his
calculations and then he just so
effectively executes on those
calculations so when you go into the max
Elephant bar deadlift which is the
opening event haor bjornson is coming
back to his compe strong man he is the
world record holder in the in the event
at 474 kg and it is expected that he
will still be a very good deadlifter in
that event if not win that event
outright because it's where he's his
strength has been forever even though
he's coming back and he's putting on
weight and all this stuff Hooper knows
that it's unlikely that he's going to
contend for top points in the Elephant
bar deadlift so he gets third place in
the Elephant bar deadlift Bobby Thompson
also an incredible static deadlifter he
comes out he only does one attempt his
opening attempt gets him second place
points very impressive and then bjon
works his way up easily scores first
place in in the max Elephant bar
deadlift the everybody speculated could
he have broken the world record it
seemed like had he just loaded over the
world record he would have had that and
then some like it was not close in in
the Elephant Bar but that said then they
went into the timber carry and this is
the first part where uh Hooper's
expectation was uh adjusted a bit to say
so Hooper is an excellent in is
excellent in this event he's going up
against Matos kisasi who has the world
record in the event from a couple years
ago he scored it in 7 Seconds which is
an insanely fast time but then the last
time that bornon did the timber carry it
was it did not go well he he did not
have the proper leverage points it was
ugly it did not look good for bjon so if
you're only able to look at past
performances in this event you would
think that this is a weak spot for bjon
not this year who boy bjon blitzed this
time on the timber carry now Mitchell
Hooper still effectively did what he
wanted to do he came within one tenth of
a second of matching KES kow's world
record which is an insanely fast time
and kis Kowski still put up a sub nsec
score for third place in the event but
Boron got second place in the timber
carry and that was a surprise that was
the first real big surprise of the
strongman weekend was that oh not only
is boron back but he's improved and
that's where when I saw that I was like
you and I thinking that bson was not
going to Podium I was like oh maybe
we're way wrong that was that was the
one moment where he that was the big
surprise the timber carry was the big
surprise so Bon has first place points
going into day two of competition Hooper
is still in the mix he's at the top
because he has a third place and a first
place in the first two events it's only
a five event two-day contest but then
Hooper's talking to the commentary team
afterwards saying hey Hooper what's your
plan what's your rundown give us give us
the the skinny and Hooper's like well we
all knew that Boron was going to win the
deadlift that's not a surprise but we
were not expecting the timber carry
however going into day two I expect to
have the best day I've ever had because
these are the events that I've been
planning for and I think you're going to
see me have the best performance I've
ever had on the apoll wheels which was
the fourth event of the competition and
everything that Hooper said is exactly
what then happened he just peered into
the future and then that is the reality
that we lived in Hooper won three
consecutive events he won the second the
third and the fourth event and in the
fifth event he had such a lead that he
only needed to beat bjon in order to
like secure it and it wasn't close so it
was tight but then day two bjornson sort
of like fell off to the point where he
lost out on his Podium position but
everything that Hooper said was just
exactly right and that's what he does at
every single contest he's in he just
knows where he is and he has no ego
about it he's like I'm best at this I'm
not at this I'm best at this I'm not at
this and he knows where everybody else
is so he calibrates where everybody else
is and goes okay well if they're going
to get this many points then I need to
get this many points he just has it down
he's going to be really tough to beat
going forward well Hooper defends Hofer
finishes in fourth place right around
the middle of the pack which Phil and I
correctly predicted just thr out there
for the haters point though he he only
lost by a half Point by a half point
it's way better than we thought way
better than we thought yeah Hooper
finishes in first K Matas Kowski a
someone whose career has been derailed
by injuries multiple times by the way
finishes in an impressive second place
and then Tom stolman in third place
right Hof Thor close by nipping and
Stan's heels in fourth one name I want
to point out that did not perform like
we maybe expected Martin's
Le's Martin is by the way one of the
funniest people I've ever interacted
with like period not even in strength
Sports and he immediately took the
social media and had a me had like the
meme ready for like his what he admitted
as a subpar performance right when he's
on he's on and when he's off he's off
and he came out and said you know what
guys I was off did not finish where I
wanted to finish martines is someone we
routinely expect to see in the top five
of the expect to see him on the podium
yeah see on the podium didn't crack it
this year let's move over to the women's
strong man or strong woman side two big
things had trouble figuring out which we
wanted to lead with I do want to talk
about Lucy underd Down's world record
Elephant bar deadlift 666 pounds
underdown finish in third overall in the
competition right but obviously kicking
things off at the Elephant bar deadlift
is exciting couple things we should know
in the Elephant bar deadlift this is a
an event unique to strong man the bar is
whippy it is lengthier than a normal
barbell the plates used have are wider
than a normal barbell that changes the
weight distribution the Elephant Bar is
designed such that you can pull more
most people can lift more with an
Elephant Bar because the weight
distribution is different than they can
with a standard deadlift bar and we
generally tend to see overall heavier
deadlifts on the Elephant Bar than a
standard bar hilariously though for both
the men and women the world record polls
are not heavier on the Elephant Bar but
that might just be because
competition standards or competition
circumstances haven't you know what I
mean but like in theory most people can
pull more in an elephant bar so let's
just get that out of the way underdown
pulls 666 pounds underdown is a 2023
Europe's strongest woman Champion comes
out of the gate swinging sets a new
world record 15 pounds heavier than
Victoria Long's Elephant bar deadlift so
a pretty significant bump up 15 pounds
underdown finishes in third overall in
the full competition Phil let talk about
who won the competition yeah so uh and
helica Jardine in her debut wins and
nobody foresaw this this being the
result and I think it's because if you
were looking at this contest like we
were ahead of time it was really hard to
place your chips anywhere other than
Victoria long defending because she was
so good in
2023 but like looking at this year
unfortunately Victoria long got injured
she she uh injured her hamstring in the
Elephant bar deadlift which she set the
world record in last year it was one of
those times where as a spectator you're
like well we had an expectation going in
that got offended by an injury what
happens now you see underdown pull the
deadlift world record like well she's
the front runner but then Thompson has a
remarkable day one you're like well
she's unbeatable and then Jardine on day
two just wait a minute who is this and
now it's just like is this the is is
Jardine just like a a front runner to
win any contest she's in now because
like it was impressive she was
impressive jarine's win I don't want to
say out of nowhere because like all
these people should be on our radar like
this is very contest not just anyone can
qualify but it actually reminds me of
Alexi novikov's world strongest man win
where a lot of people were surprised and
suddenly it's you're heading into the
final or the final couple events and
you're like sorry who who's this you
know now novakov is is a player in the
space and I wonder if that's what we're
gonna see from Angelico Jardine but it
just kind of reminded me of Alexi
novakov the World's Strongest Man win
from a few years exactly I think the
novakov analogy is pretty strong with
Jardine because like now my eye is gonna
be on her for every contest she's
entered as like okay that that's a
Podium Contender well I'm thrilled I got
the Phil Blackman seal of approval let's
move on to maybe the big upset of the
weekend so let's talk about the classic
physique contest Wesley
vissers I'm not gonna say he came out of
nowhere but he finished in seventh place
last year guess what he finished this
year first and the heavy front runner
Phil let's talk about the heavy front
runner coming into this contest yeah I
mean Ramon Dino has been the the front
runner outside of Bumstead he's been the
top guy in the classic physique division
for the past two years he's been the
runner up at the Olympia to Bumstead and
Bumstead as we talked about before he's
just like if if Bumstead ever loses that
would be the shock of the century in
this sport because he is the standard of
the division the physique that they base
everyone else off of is exactly
bumstead's physique so to beat what the
judges are templating off of is just I
mean it would it it seems unfathomable
but Ramon has been the top guy next to
Bumstead as the top two like clear ahead
of everybody else for the past two years
V has been in the mix but he's been
outside the top four the top four the
last two years has been very steadily
Bumstead rot
ear cisinski and Brion who's and they've
been in that order pretty steadily all
the way through and Vis was on the
outside looking in but he was always in
the mix he's in the top six he's in the
top seven and then vissers is in the
final call out against Ramone in
prejudging and everybody's like what is
happening what is going on is this is
this V's time because he Lea frogged
over s and those guys train together so
ERS is still in the same spot that he
was but V leap frogs and everybody is
like wait a minute what Isen happening
is this is this a huge shakeup Wesley
came in bigger he had a different uh way
of posing to like hide the fact that his
waist is just naturally wider than
Ramones is Ramon has a very very
naturally narrow waist which helps
emphasize the x-frame of his physique
viser changed his up changed up his
posing to like help maintain that big
bigger x-frame he also came in as just
the bigger guy and so now what we were
talking about before of how momentum and
Optics mean a lot in a subjective sport
we looking at the Olympia and going wait
a minute okay well we know what the top
four was but now V is in the mix and
it's like is vissers actually going to
be standing next to Bumstead in Final
Call outs like what what do we expect
now for the Olympia vissers being the
Arnold Champion throws an interesting
variable and we might see a mixup
because we have not seen the top tier at
the Olympia and men's classic Phi change
at all the last two years the ordering
has been the same it's been the same
story it's been exciting right the
journey to get there has been exciting
and noteworthy and watchable but now
vissers is in the convers like that this
is this is it I like this rone finishes
in second place right but suddenly again
you talk about like Champions
potentially losing momentum Ramone
always kind of has used the last couple
years the Arnold Classic as a way to
build momentum winning that okay he's
the Challenger to
Bumstead now he V's the Challenger to
Bumstead has raone lost momentum from
getting in SEC second place here it's
super fascinating I think that when you
looked at the top three from the last
couple of years at the Olympia it was
always s and third behind Ramone and
Bumstead and there was always talk of
like we've covered s pretty
significantly on on barbin and there's
been times where it's like okay this
dude is got so much mass that it's like
this dude should just go up to the men's
open because he's carrying so much
muscle he actually has to like Drop
muscle in order to make weight and so it
was just assumed that if Ramon wasn't
actually going to take the title from
brumstead that ERS was like sort of next
in line to like challenge for the throne
as he made progress and so to see that
in 's like still holding his spot but
that viser just leap frogged over
everybody that like shows the
significant difference that he was able
to bring in his package and that's
really where this big shakeup is because
if a shakeup was going to happen we also
had an expectation of what that shakeup
might look like and that shakeup is now
happening but it's not what we were
expecting and so that's why it's also
more shocking because the person that
beat Ramone wasn't s also want to point
out ERS did finish in third and comes
away with the best poser award so uh
which is interesting because V what he
did with his posing was really
interesting but uh ERS does take the the
best poser award and gets an additional
10K so just want to point that out Phil
the Olympia weekend is maybe G to be the
most exciting one we've been going into
for a while there are tons more
divisions we could cover that's all we
have time for in strength weekly for
baron.com I'm David Thomas T joined by
the expert of experts I'm Phil Blackman
thank you so much for watching our
Arnold Classic coverage on barbend if
you missed out on any of it it is still
all live and it is very exciting as we
head in to the rest of the bodybuilding
season and the rest of the strong men
and strong women season this has been
strength weekly thanks for
[Music]
watching